A Guide to the Papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell Relating to the Founding of the University of Virginia,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 February 1, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 113-114. (Box-folder 1:40)
  Loan offered by John Brockenbrough, President of the Bank of Virginia, better than can be obtained from Benjamin Hatcher of the Farmer's Bank. Necessity for the Visitors to sign the notes as individuals. References to Wilson C. Nicholas and David Watson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 February 6, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Partly printed: Cabell 1 16-1 18. (Box-folder 1:41)
  Inquiries regarding Poinsot des Essarts' land patents. Back-country opposition to T. J.'s general education bill. Opposition to Central College from friends of Lexington and Staunton. Recommends selection of men such as General [John George] Jackson in the Northwest of Virginia and William Burwell from the Southwest. References to Mr. Johnson, General Kosciuszko, and Peter Carr.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 February 10, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 119-121. (Box-folder 1:42)
  T. J.'s letter published in the Enquirer to help the general education bill, omitting T. J.'s estimate of the large amount of money necessary. Reference to William Cabell, Wilson C. Nicholas, and Lewis Somers (i.e., Summers).
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 February 12, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 121-122. (Box-folder 1:43)
  Introducing Lewis Summers of Kanawha County.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 February 13, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Partly printed: Cabell 122123. (Box-folder 1:44)
  Enquiries regarding Poinsot des Essarts' land. Failure of T. J.'s general education bill, with only a small appropriation for education of the poor, due to interests from Lexington and Staunton and to the Presbyterians, aided by a junto from the middle country delegation (Charles Yancey, Thomas Miller, Robert Mallory, and Charles Everett). Possibility of an appropriation for Central College. References to Francis T. Brooke, Dabney Carr, John W. Green, Thomas Hill, and Chapman Johnson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 February 20, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 125-126. (Box-folder 1:45)
  Bill providing for education of poor, an appropriation for the University, and the setting up of the Rockfish Gap Commission passed the Senate.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 February 22, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Partly printed: Cabell 127. (Box-folder 1:46)
  Passage of the Rockfish Gap Bill. Asks T. J. to serve as a commissioner. Appointments in the hands of the president and directors of the Literary Fund, three fifths of whom are from beyond the mountains. Urges immediate work on buildings of Central College because of opposition from Federalists, Presbyterian clergy, and the entire back country. Mentions James Madison.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Fluvanna County, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 March 11, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 129. (Box-folder 1:47)
  Selection of members of the Rockfish Gap Commission. Visit to Monticello.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 March 15, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 130-132. (Box-folder 1:48)
  Rivalry between Washington College, Rockbridge College, and Central College as to the site for the University. Offer by a Mr. Robinson of Lexington to leave his estate to the University if located there. Requests T. J. to urge Wilson J. Cary, John Hartwell Cocke, Randolph Harrison, and Washington Trueheart to serve in House of Delegates as friends of Central College. References to John Wayles Eppes.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, at Mrs. Tinsley's, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 March 31, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 132. (Box-folder 1:49)
  Lending Jefferson a copy of the Oxford and Cambridge guide.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 July 30, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 132-133. (Box-folder 1:50)
  Sends by his brother William the signatures of Central College subscribers in Nelson County, agreeing to the conveyance of the property of Central College to the Commonwealth of Virginia, if the University of Virginia is located on the site of the college.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 October 24, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 133-134. (Box-folder 1:51)
  Invitation to Warminster; urges him not to tax his health.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Enniscorthy, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 November 18, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 134-135. (Box-folder 1:52)
  Illness prevents visit to Monticello. Rockfish Gap Report. Reason why he cannot make the trip to Europe for the college. Possibility he may run for the House of Representatives. Information regarding the hill for locating the University. Mentions [Samuel] Carr, Isaac Coles, William F. Gordon, Spencer Roane, Francis T. Brooke.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 December 8, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 137-138. (Box-folder 1:53)
  Progress of the Rockfish Gap Report in the General Assembly. Attitudes of the William and Mary and Lexington interests. Cabell's health. References to Samuel Carr, William F. Gordon, Samuel Taylor, and Philip R. Thompson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 December 14, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Partly printed: Cabell 138-139. (Box-folder 1:54)
  Progress of the bill to decide the site of the University. Prospects of Central College. Report of T. J.'s authorship of the bill gives appearance of dictation. References to Linn Banks, Samuel Taylor, and Robert T. Thompson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 December 17, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 139-140. (Box-folder 1:55)
  Central College fixed as the site of the University in the bill reported to the House of Delegates. Combination of western delegates opposed to Central College. Publication of T. J.'s calculation of the center of population based on census of 1810. References to Wilson C. Nicholas and William Cabell.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 December 17, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 141. (Box-folder 1:56)
  Senator Davidson [Davison?] of Clarksburg in favor of Central College.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 December 24, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 141-144. (Box-folder 1:57)
  Delay of the University bill. Opposition from friends of William and Marv, who demand $5000 per annum for William and Mary as price of their concurrence, from those who wish education left to individual enterprise, and from those who wish Literary Fund devoted to the poor. Various methods of calculating the center of population. References to the Edinburgh Review, William S. Archer, James Hunter, Chapman Johnson, Francis Preston, Adam Smith, Dugald Stewart, and Colonel Tatham.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 January 7, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 146-149. (Box-folder 1:58)
  Cabell's labors in the General Assembly on behalf of the University Bill. T. J.'s health. References to John Brockenbrough, Chancellor John W. Green, Thomas C. Holmes, W. C. Nicholas, Mr. Pannel, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., Spencer Roane, Mr. Slaughter, John Taliaferro, Samuel Taylor, Chancellor [Creed] Taylor, and Philip Thompson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 January 18, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 149-152. (Box-folder 1:59)
  University Bill passes the House of Delegates with Central College fixed as the site. Various methods of determining the center of population favor Central College. Cabell's recent illness. References to Briscoe G. Baldwin, Dabney Carr, Armistead Holmes, and James Hunter.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 January 21, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 152-153. (Box-folder 1:60)
  Progress of the University Bill in the Senate. Bill to connect the eastern and western waters. Cabell's ill-health. References to Judge John Coalter, George Hay, Armistead Holmes, Chapman Johnson, Alfred Powell, John Taliaferro, and Philip Thompson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 January 25, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 153. (Box-folder 1:61)
  Passage of the University Bill. Cabell's illness. References to John Coalter, Chapman Johnson, and Edward Watts.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 February 4, LS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed by Cabell 155-159, misdated as of 4 December. (Box-folder 1:62)
  Advises against moving now for the derelict portion of the School Fund. Copy of reports on the navigation of the James and on connection of eastern and western waters. Sketch of services rendered by the following friends of the University: William Brockenbrough, William H. Brodnax, Francis T. Brooke, Samuel Carr, John Coalter, [Francis W.?] Gilmer (author of essays signed "a Virginian"), John W. Green, George Hay, Armistead Holmes, Garrett Minor, Wilson C. Nicholas, George Nicholson, Mr. Pannel, the Rev. Mr. Rice (author of essay signed "Crito"), Mr. Ritchie, Judge Spencer Roane, James Robertson, JF., Mr. Scott, Captain Slaughter, Mr. Stannard, John Taliaferro, Chancellor [Creed] Taylor, Philip Thompson. Mentions also William S. Archer, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., and James Madison. (Thirteen lines made illegible, probably prior to publication of N. F. Cabell's book).
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 February 8, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Also includes: J. Brown to Thomas Jefferson. 1819 February 8. ALS. 2 pp. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 159-161. (Box-folder 1:63)
  Revenue of the Literary Fund not equal to appropriations.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 February 15, ALS. 3 pp. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Endorsed by T. J. Printed: Cabell 161-163. (Box-folder 1:64)
  Appointment of James Breckenridge, Joseph Cabell, John Hartwell Cocke, Chapman Johnson, James Madison, and Robert B. Taylor as Visitors of the University of Virginia. Cabell's health. Untrue report that Cabell is to go to Europe to seek professors. Advises delay in opening the University until sufficient buildings are ready. References to Samuel Taylor, Armistead Holmes, [Samuel] Carr, and Henry St. George Tucker.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 February 22, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 165-167. (Box-folder 1:65)
  Meeting of the Board of Visitors of University; appointment of Dr. Cooper one of great delicacy and importance; recommends delay in opening until several eminent professors are secured. Difficulties in securing adequate funds from the Assembly. References to James Breckenridge, John Hartwell Cocke, Isaac Coles, James Madison, Robert B. Taylor, and David Watson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 March 8, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Partly printed: Cabell 170-172. (Box-folder 1:66)
  State funds for the University. The Literary Fund. Professorship offered to Thomas Cooper. References to John Hartwell Cocke, Isaac Coles, Alexander Garrett, James Madison, and James P. Preston.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 March 12, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 173-174. (Box-folder 1:67)
  Advertisement for workmen for the University inserted in the Enquirer. Alexander Garrett's draft on Literary Fund will be honored. Importance of securing Arthur Spicer Brockenbrough as proctor. Cabell's health improved. Mentions Mary Cabell, Mr. Montcarel, and Wilson C. Nicholas.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 April 17, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 174-176. (Box-folder 1:68)
  Recommends A. S. Brockenbrough as Proctor. Despite admiration for T. J.'s plans for the pavilions and lawn, recommends different style for hotels and ranges. Provision for lecture rooms in separate buildings from pavilions. Fire at Monticello. Reference to John Hartwell Cocke.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Bremo, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1819 November 2, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 177. (Box-folder 1:69)
  Returns copy of plan of Poplar Forest. Financial requirements prevent his moving to the neighborhood of the University at the present time. T. J.'s illness.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1820 February 3, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 180-181. (Box-folder 1:70)
  Funds for the University from Literary Fund and elsewhere. Health of his wife, Mary. Reference to Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1820 February 17, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 181-182 (Box-folder 1:71)
  Attempts to obtain money for the University from the Assembly. References to William and Mary, Burwell Bassett, James Breckenridge, James Dickinson, George Hay, and Chapman Johnson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1820 February 24, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 182-183. (Box-folder 1:72)
  Encloses bill just passed regarding funds for the University. References to James Breckenridge, William F. Gordon, and Chapman Johnson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Charlottesville, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1820 October 3, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 183. (Box-folder 1:73)
  Verification of Alexander Garrett's account.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1820 December 20, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Partly printed: Cabell 189-190. (Box-folder 1:74)
  Attack on Governor Randolph's character. Money from the Assembly for University. Requests fuller accounts by Bursar, Mr. Garrett. References to James Breckenridge, Mary Cabell, Chapman Johnson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1820 December 22, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Partly printed: Cabell 190-192. (Box-folder 1:75)
  Resolution giving grants to William and Mary, Hampton-Sidney, Washington College, New London Academy, and the University will defeat the claims of the University on the Literary Fund. Attitude of James Breckenridge, John Bowyer, John Coalter, George W. Crump, Philip Doddridge, David S. Garland, William F. Gordon, Mr. [Richard] Morris, Thomas Miller, Isaac Otey, Jr., Judge Spencer Roane, Mr. [William?] Taylor, and David Watson. Alexander Garrett's account for the University. Comments on Governor Randolph's message.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 January 4, ALS. 2 pp. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Endorsed by T. J. Printed: Cabell 194-195. (Box-folder 1:76)
  Funds for the University. Doctrine that all colleges receiving funds should be under the control of the legislature. References to William and Mary, Mr. Bassett, Samuel Blackburn, Philip Doddridge, David S. Garland, Thomas Griffin, Chapman Johnson, Thomas Miller, [James?] Smith, Richard Venable, and Henry E. Watkins.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 January 18, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 196-197. (Box-folder 1:77)
  Little prospect of gaining additional funds for the University. References to Mr. Broadnax, [Richard?] Morris, and [Samuel] Taylor.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 January 25, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 197-199. (Box-folder 1:78)
  Funds for the University. Plans to leave public life at end of present session. References to James Breckenridge, [Nathaniel?] Claiborne, John Hartwell Cocke, Chapman Johnson, and James P. Preston.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 February 8, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 203-204. (Box-folder 1:79)
  Agrees to be a candidate for Assembly again. Funds for the University. References to Samuel Blackburn, James Breckenridge, Chapman Johnson, and William Selden.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 February 20, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 204-206. (Box-folder 1:80)
  Meeting of the Board of Visitors. Funds for the University. Passage of James River Bill by House of Delegates. References to William Archer, James Breckenridge, William Brodnax, Armistead Currie, David S. Garland, Chapman Johnson, Robert Mallory, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., Samuel Taylor, and Robert B. Taylor.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 February 22, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 206. (Box-folder 1:81)
  Funds for the University. References to Samuel Blackburn, [Nathaniel?] Claiborne, and David S. Garland.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 February 25, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 208-209. (Box-folder 1:82)
  Passage of bill providing funds for the University. Mentions Samuel Blackburn, James Breckenridge, John Bowyer, William B. Chamberlayne, George W. Crump, Armistead Currie, William F. Gordon, James Hunter, Chapman Johnson, George Loyall, Richard Morris, Mr. Stephenson, and David Watson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 March 10, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 210-212. (Box-folder 1:83)
  Advises building no more buildings than those for which there is money in hand. Urges Jefferson to use his influence in the election of friends of the University. References to James Breckenridge, William H. Brodnax, Samuel Taylor, Littleton Tazewell, and Mr. Watts.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 April 1, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 212. (Box-folder 1:84)
  Reasons for inability to attend meeting of the Board of Visitors. Note sent by [Valentine?] Southall.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Henrico County, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 April 28, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 212-214. (Box-folder 1:85)
  Cabell's illness. Requests information regarding last meeting of the Board of Visitors. Success of Samuel Blackburn, James Breckenridge, David S. Garland, Mr. Maury of Buckingham, and Joseph Shelton in the recent election. Funds for the University.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 August 5, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 215-216. (Box-folder 1:86)
  Cabell's illness. Request for complete statement of all University accounts for the next General Assembly. Attacks on the University by the Presbyterians of Hampton-Sydney and the Episcopalians of William and Mary. Washington College to receive Robinson's estate.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 August 31, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 217-218. (Box-folder 1:87)
  Meeting of the Board of Visitors. Cabell's health. Reference to Mary Cabell.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1821 November 21, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 222-223. (Box-folder 1:88)
  Absence from the meeting of the Board of Visitors due to illness. Advisability of finishing all University buildings. University finances. References to Chapman Johnson and Dr. [John A.] Smith of Williamsburg.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1822 January 7, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Partly printed: Cabell 229231. (Box-folder 1:89)
  Funds for the University. Reasons for Thomas Griffin's resolution. Opposition from the clergy. References to William and Mary, Hampden-Sydney, Chapman Johnson, Bishop [Richard Channing] Moore, Richard Morris, Rev. Mr. Rice, and Henry E. Watkins.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1822 January 14, ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Partly printed: Cabell 231-237. (Box-folder 1:90)
  Funds for the University. Advises conciliation of the clergy who are uneasy because of the predominance of the Socinians at Cambridge (Harvard), the appointment of Thomas Cooper in South Carolina, and the discovery that George Ticknor and Nathaniel Bowditch are Unitarians. References to Chapman Johnson and David Watson.